<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Off-by-mind blog</title>
    <link>https://anaderi.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Off-by-mind blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 13:52:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://anaderi.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Поиск очень редких событий в LHCb</title>
      <link>https://anaderi.github.io/2016/09/24/bs2mu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 13:52:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anaderi.github.io/2016/09/24/bs2mu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Одним из основных подходов к анализу данных в физике высоких энергий является численный анализ. Этот подход используется при исследовании редких процессов, таких как появление бозона Хиггса или распад B-мезона на два мюона (B → µµ). Этот распад интересен тем, что его частота в соответствии со стандартной моделью: а) очень низкая — около 10 в степени −9; б) значительно меньше частоты, предсказываемой некоторыми «суперсимметричными» моделями. Другими словами, наблюдение отклонений от предсказаний стандартной модели могло стать убедительным свидетельством существования частиц, которых никто ещё не видел!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Адаптировано под аудиторию, для которой слова &amp;ldquo;градиентный бустинг&amp;rdquo; гораздо понятней, чем &amp;ldquo;квантовая хромодинамика&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;101f3d6368c245e792acc071e4d22c72&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Замечательне доклады Владимира Шевченко, Федора Ратникова и Тани Лихоманенко о работе с данными в физике высоких энергий можно найти на странице мероприятия
&lt;a href=&#34;https://events.yandex.ru/events/ds/17-sept-2016/&#34;&gt;https://events.yandex.ru/events/ds/17-sept-2016/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about author &amp; blog</title>
      <link>https://anaderi.github.io/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 17:06:05 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anaderi.github.io/page/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m head of &lt;a href=&#34;https://yandexdataschool.com&#34;&gt;Yandex School of Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt; research group and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.hse.ru/lambda&#34;&gt;Laboratory of Methods of Big Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://hse.ru&#34;&gt;Higher School of Economics&lt;/a&gt;. Those groups are focused on solving data-intensive tasks from various areas of natural sciences using machine learning techniques. For example members of my team are taking part in &lt;a href=&#34;https://lhcb.web.cern.ch/lhcb/&#34;&gt;LHCb&lt;/a&gt; experiment at &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.cern&#34;&gt;CERN&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://crayfis.io&#34;&gt;CRAYFIS collaboration&lt;/a&gt; and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; embrace various stuff from biologically engineered pet-food recipes designed by deep learning to music composition history, but mostly it is going focus on such things as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;human mind, consciousness, mindfulness,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;machine intelligence, data science, meta and fundamental science,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reproducibility, errors and coincidences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mainly because I&amp;rsquo;m more sensitive to those. And the main motivation for posting here is getting a better grasp of the content of own mind (sometimes I wish there could be such things as &amp;lsquo;contents&amp;rsquo; to the mind as it is for a regular book). In other words I make posts not to make a pleasant reading, but to make own thoughts a bit more tangible for myself 😄. If you find some of those posts interesting as well - I&amp;rsquo;d be very happy - just leave a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile if you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn a bit more about projects of my team, you&amp;rsquo;re welcome browse it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yandexdataschool&#34;&gt;github repositories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>off-by-mind?</title>
      <link>https://anaderi.github.io/2016/08/04/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 17:05:38 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anaderi.github.io/2016/08/04/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Dear diary, &amp;hellip;&lt;/del&gt; 😄&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TwoHardThings.html&#34;&gt;popular saying&lt;/a&gt; that in Computer Science there are only 2 hard things: naming, cache invalidation &amp;hellip; and &lt;em&gt;off-by-one&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those &lt;em&gt;off-by-one&lt;/em&gt; relate to an error of accessing array elements in logically incorrect order. You can have many errors of that kind even in a short piece of code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [-2, -1, 0, -1, -2]
for i in range(1, 5): # error_1 - omitting 1st element
    if a[i] &amp;lt; 0: a.remove(a[i]) # error_2, altering list inside iterator
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;running it would result in exception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34;&gt;IndexError: list index out of range
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually the code above is quite nasty, but why do I bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like arrays store numbers, human mind store &amp;amp; process &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meme&#34;&gt;memes&lt;/a&gt;. So occasional writing to unprepared mind might look completely similar to off-by-one error. The difference is that there is no entity to check boundary condition and subjectively it is treated as learning something new or addicting to something unexpected. Also it is not treated as an &lt;em&gt;error&lt;/em&gt; at all, and instead of exception we get involved in discussions, rants or just writing blog posts. So as more memes continue hitting my mind I&amp;rsquo;d respond to some of them with a blog post that without much further explanation could be called &lt;em&gt;off-by-mind&lt;/em&gt; posts and so is called the blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt; also the date seems to be rather good excuse for the start &lt;code&gt;16 - 08 - 04&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>